JUAN C. CONTRERAS

jcontrmo@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/juancontrmo/

Certified professional Developer (Oracle Forms - PLSQL - SQL) and Database administrator, in addition to Oracle Data Integrator (ODI) support experience helping customers to solve issues related to ELT mappings , performance, bug documentation, patching, testing, and ELT development. Skilled problem identifier and troubleshooter in a range of IT environments with certified knowledge of Oracle Cloud Infrastructure (OCI); Bilingual English-Spanish, US citizen with employment history verified through an external company, see www.hireright.com.

Objective

Looking for challenging Database Developer positions according to my knowledge and experience (SQL + Data Modeling + PL/SQL + ELT + Database Administration).

Summary of Skills

Oracle PLSQL Developer, Oracle Forms, Bash Shell, O	Beginner Level: Oracle APEX, , Oracle Cloud, Python, GIT, OEM, GoldenGate
---	---

Education

<u>Universidad Antonio Nariño</u> – BS – Systems Engineering Bogota, D.C 1998

Certifications

- Oracle PL/SQL Certified Associate
- Oracle Cloud Infrastructure Foundations
- Oracle Database Administrator
- Oracle Forms Developer

Technical videos:

YouTube channel <u>"JC Contreras – Just a curious Tech Guy"</u>
 Media channel with videos for Database Developers

Video #1: Data Integration example between Oracle and SQL Server Video #2: Connecting Oracle SQLDeveloper to OCI & AWS (Part I) Video #3: Connecting Oracle SQLDeveloper to OCI & AWS (Part II)

Languages:

- English Advance Proficiency
- Spanish Native

Resume Spanish translation: https://jcontrmo.github.io/HojaVida/

Professional Experience

<u>ORACLE</u> – Senior Technical Support Engineer Orlando USA, FL Oct 21,2015 – Jul 15,2020

- Creation of ODI Source-target mapping among different technologies, reverse engineering, models generation, create package steps of different types, modified and developed knowledge modules, using mapping components and expressions, use variables in packages and several development techniques as part of internal training and issue reproduction to solve service requests.
- Troubleshooting simple to complex Oracle data integrator issues for top account customers under SLAs predefined
- ODI upgrades from 11g to 12c versions for internal testing
- English-Spanish translator through phone calls and web conference to help Engineers colleagues to provide support in ODI related issues.
- Configuration and design of virtual environments (database, OS, ODI agents) on Linux and Windows platforms to reproduce and solve ODI technical issues.
- ODI Topology Configuration to handle data integration connectivity with several source & target technologies
- Tuning of ODI developments, Memory, IO checking to provide best practices to improve ODI performance
- Documentation of solved issues to be published on my Oracle Support site
- Code review (PLSQL, Bash shell) to troubleshoot ODI issues
- Load data into Oracle tables using SQL Loader
- Verification of Database, OS System, WebLogic logs and Network to troubleshoot ODI issues

INDRA – Database Administrator Bogota, D.C. July 9,2012 – Jan 31,2014

- Installed, configured, and managed Oracle 10g, 11g on windows and Linux platform.
- Interacted with the Technical Design team and contributed in impact analysis and creation of the technical specifications.
- Manage Database administration assignments in SQL Server environments
- Worked on Oracle databases and MSSQL, this included backup, restoration, and quality control
 applications.
- Developed windows scripts, shell scripts, PL/SQL programming for automation of database administration tasks
- Detailed review of Oracle Forms and PL/SQL code on customers to troubleshoot performance issues as part of the customer's software design.
- Developed and created a definition of backup strategies for RMAN and EXPDP.
- Created database structures for developer and client needs on QA and production environments.
- Applied security patches on Oracle databases.
- Involved in session management and monitoring the critical wait events, blocking sessions in the databases (Oracle and MSSQL).
- Worked on Migration of Oracle 11g Databases from Windows to Linux on Production environment

<u>EUD</u> – IT Certification Trainer Bogota, D.C. July 2011 – July 2012

- Training IT students in Database Administration, PL/SQL and Oracle Forms programming by using official Oracle documentation in order to help them to achieve Oracle Certifications.
- Installed databases and OS in classroom environments.

 Provided recommendations to real issues happening on students' jobs related to PLSQL coding and Oracle Forms design according to best practices

SYNAPSIS (TIVIT) - Oracle Database Administrator Bogota, D.C May 5, 2010 – Dec 31, 2011

- Managed Oracle RMAN backups and tuning oracle sentences.
- Provided support for Oracle Data Guard administration
- Oracle database and MSSQL backups and recovery.
- Added more new features to existing analysis software tools.
- Created structural changes to the Oracle databases using DDL statements.
- Worked on Oracle configuration, third party backup software and backup testing.
- Supported DBA Junior SQL Server 2008 on replication scenario with log shipping.
- Made corrections of inefficient high load SQL statements, suboptimal use of Oracle database, undersized memory structures, concurrency issues, database configuration, and locking issues.
- Created Bash Shell scripts to invoke SQL Scripts and scheduled them using OS crontab
- Developed Complex PL/SQL Code, Stored Procedures, Functions, Packages and Triggers which uses collections as part of temporary developments assignments
- Applied analysis, data collection techniques, database normalization, entity relation modeling in SDLC from analysis, design, development, testing, implementation, and maintenance
- Reports generation based on multiple tables and subqueries by using ANSI SQL and T-SQL
- Involved in data loading using SQL Loader to load data from flat files
- Worked closely with clients to clarify development specifications

<u>Telefónica (Movistar)</u> – IT Database Professional – Bogotá, DC Nov 3, 2009 – Apr 1, 2010

- Utilize Oracle diagnostic tools like Explain Plan, SQL Trace, TKPROF and AWR to analyze timing and execution for database tuning
- Created and modified existing Unix scripts for Oracle 10g
- Managed Standard Audit trail, audit parameters
- Used triggers to record additional customized Audit information
- Worked with the development team for database object creation, query tuning and regular database related issues.
- Oracle database installation, patch installation, configuration, and maintenance.
- Tune the SQL queries by creating proper index, using hints, and changing database parameters
- Involved in development of application functions, triggers, PL/SQL and packages
- 24 x 7 database on call support according to shift rotation schedule

ORATECH LTDA

Aug 19, 2008 - Jul 22, 2009

Position: Infrastructure Consultant

- Managed the Oracle database (RAC-Standby-ASM).
- Acted as a consultant for software development tools, PL / SQL-forms-reports.
- Trained clients in Oracle database administration.
- Supported DBA clients (Falabella, Colombian Army, Thomas Express, Movistar).
- Visited clients on business sites, provided quotes configuration and created systems reports for clients and management.

SBD LTDA

October 2007 – August 2008

Position: Oracle Database Administrator

- Created users and privileges according with their responsibilities
- Configuring backup and restore procedures with RMAN scripts
- Tuned Oracle Sentences
- Developed scripts with PL / SQL and Shell scripting on Unix environments for DBA automated tasks
- Created and interpreting statspack reports
- Supported on call 24/7 DBA .

GEOSPATIAL

April 2007 - October 2007

Position: Development Leader Database

- Managed the Oracle development team on activities related with PL / SQL and Oracle Forms-Reports programming.
- Geodatabase Modeling, Use Case Specification
- Analyzed and design solutions according to the client requirements using RUP methodology
- Meeting clients face to face and on site to ascertain requirements.
- Producing and updating relevant documentation.

INFORMATICA SIGLO 21

November 2005 - March 2007 Position: Consulting Engineer

- Oracle10g Programming (Forms Builder, Reports Builder, PL / SQL)
- Development of New Buildings module and ranking contractors in Gas Natural ESP
- Application Maintenance NGV (Natural Gas Vehicle), IVM (Integrated Management of Sales), SAT
- Analyzed user requirements with UML methodology
- Design and Implementation of Business Applications using the Oracle Relational Database Management System (RDBMS).

SOFTMANAGEMENT

August 2003 - September 2005 Position: Senior Programmer

- Developed Complex database objects like Stored Procedures, Functions, Packages and Triggers using SQL and PL/SQL.
- Data analysis and generation of scripts for running reports
- Data analysis and generation of scripts for modification of information
- Change displays and programs Front-End, according to new requirements of the business.
- Programming Oracle (Forms 6i, PL / SQL and Reports), Procedures, Packages and Functions

- Involved in the support, maintenance, and development of the financial system
- Defining and generating screen formats and report designs using Oracle Forms and Oracle Reports
- Developed in accordance with policies regarding secure coding & standards
- Carrying out design, construction, review, and defect analysis activities.
- Developed using Oracle (Forms 6i, PL / SQL and Reports) in accordance with agreed design with consideration for usability, software quality and future maintenance

AVANZIT TECNOLOGÍA (new name Ezentis)

June 2000 - February 2002 Position: Oracle Developer

- Analysis and Design of security database modules
- Administration of databases in development and testing environment
- Project coordination SIGART for public sector telecommunication company
- Training for application users

SYNERSIS S.A.S

September 1999 - June 2000 Position: Oracle Developer

- Analysis, design and programming of the human resources Information System
- Oracle Development using (Forms 4.5, Reports 2.5, SQLPLUS).
- Testing on QA environments for new software
- Defining and generating screen formats and report designs.
- Produced and updatied relevant documentation for new developments.
- Develop software in accordance with agreed design with consideration for usability, software quality and future maintenance.

SOFTBOLIVAR - SEGUROS BOLIVAR

April 1998 – June 1999 Position: Oracle Developer

- Design and development of programs and reports for capitalization products
- Oracle Development using Forms 4.5, Reports 2.5, SQLPLUS

PERSONAL ACHIEVEMENTS

- **B**e able to adapt professionally and linguistically to support my family after moving from the country which I was born to the US 6 years ago.
- 5k runner in Orlando FL during two consecutive years
- Join the Catholic Christian community as an active member

JOB REFERENCES

Please check my LinkedIn connections, some of them know me very well.